We're going to be in my city council except number 18, 20, 23.
Number two, automation declaring September 22nd, 2023 as Barbara Lauren Day.
Motion.
Second.
Seconded.
Wait.
Don't hold.
Aye.
Senator Williams.
Parker.
Aye.
By the way, Central Avenue Bridge, to honor Chief Edwin Cook.
And for those of you that don't know, Chief Cook passed away yesterday.
And this bridge was something she was very proud of.
Her first go as a chief, her first time as a chief,
she joined the city and helped make this bridge happen.
So Friday morning, her daughter Samantha had messaged me and
said that her mom wanted to see Bo and I.
So we went out to see her.
Luckily, we had a really good conversation with her.
You'll hear a little bit about that in a minute too.
But after we left, I told Bo I wanted to name that bridge after her.
Because I knew she was proud of that and being a part of that.
But I told him I didn't want to wait until she was gone.
I wanted her to know before she was gone.
So Bo, the city staff, pulled a miracle off and
had this thing where I could go tell her within a few hours.
So I went back to her house and walked in and her daughter said she's asleep.
She's been asleep since you and Bo left this morning.
I said, well, I need to tell you something.
I said, I will tell you and your dad and maybe she'll over here.
And so I said to Central Bridge, our council meeting,
we're planning on voting to name this after her.
And so she was asleep and she said, I love you, boys.
So she heard it and she knew.
So that made me happy that she knew.
I had Bo on the phone and I wanted to tell her so.
But it would be a great honor to drive by there and
see her name on the sign every time we drive by.
So I need a motion to approve.
Second.
William.
Senator.
Senator Sharif.
So, Kay, Bowman.
I understand the seating that you all are going to be discussing and
deliberating on allowing the Boys and
Girls Club of Ottawa County to create and build a gymnasium.
That for the use of our teens and the older kids in this county.
I really don't have a political thing on this.
I'm a member of the Friends of the Coleman.
I've been president of Miami Little Theater.
But I was a teacher in this school district for 30 years.
And I continue to advocate for children.
All Saints Episcopal Church does Teacher's Toolbox,
which provides school supplies for every student in Ottawa County.
I'm also on the Miami Public Schools Enrichment Foundation.
I'm on the Arts and Humanities Council.
And all of those things promote children and our youth.
And so I'm here to say that I really hope that you approve
creating a gymnasium on the existing building.
I know that it's taking some space as a parking, but
I think we still have enough to share.
And the vision that this gives to our young people is invaluable.
They need to know that this community and this city has their back.
And the best place I know for them to be is within the heart of the city.
So they can be learning about the things that happen here.
They would be in the thought within walking distance to the Coleman.
They are the future audience for the Coleman.
They can be used to help promote that place.
They have been used.
We used them at the Mural Fest this year with Arts and Humanities.
They were wonderful helpers who tromped up and
down Main Street on a really, really hot day,
making sure that everyone was comfortable and ready.
Our children need our support.
And so I ask today that you really consider heavily that these kids
are our most important future, and that if we say that they are not
important, then we are really cutting our throats.
Please consider this.
They are invaluable, and you must, must remember that they're your future voters.
They learn, they pay attention, and they remember.
I still talk to students, well, they're adults now, and
they're all grandparents, practically.
But when this community voted down in auditorium for this school district,
it was heartfelt and is still a sore spot for people in the 70s.
We're talking 50 years ago, folks.
That's something that we need to remember, that this kind of vote.
And we need another gymnasium.
Our schools don't have enough space for our kids.
We don't have a YMCA, or other places that our kids can gather.
And the Boys and Girls Club offers a variety of programs,
not just athletic, but studying, arts,
a variety of things that will improve our community.
The world is a different place than it was when I started teaching here in 1975.
And we have a lot of parents who try their best.
But the homes that our kids grow up in now are vastly different than
the ones from 50 years ago.
Thank you.
Okay, next we have Jessica Mullen, claims.
Parker.
All right, six, September 5th, 2023, Bravers, go to mute.
Sundberg, Williams, Sokol.
Seven, discussion on ordinance to protect citizens.
Misty Tiffany, moving on to eight, we'll move on to nine.
Discussion with Remsa Coleman, the Boys and Girls Club,
regarding the proposal to build a gymnasium and parking lot.
Of the Boys and Girls Club, Kingsland, Carol.
Mayor Parker, council members.
The city has abandoned its offer to sell part of the parking lot,
circumventing any issues with the sale of public property,
to an offer to lease part of the lot.
Do the council members know the answers to these questions tonight?
Does the city know its fiduciary liability for this project?
Do individual board members of the club have personal, legal,
and fiduciary liabilities?
Is the builder prepared to cover the cost of an environmental study
below all that concrete and a water runoff study by a certified
engineer before construction can begin?
But all of that is of no concern, because here's the issue for tonight.
The land for all the city parking lots on both eight streets
was purchased with a federal urban renewal grant
through the Miami Urban Development Authority.
On May 6, 1968, the Miami Urban Development Authority
transferred by warranty deed the parking lots to the city of Miami,
Oklahoma, with reservations, restrictions, and protective covenants.
The city agreed for itself, its successors, and assigns,
and every successor in interest to the restrictions.
The first restriction is that the property can be used only for
all street parking.
After consultation with our title attorney, we know that
restriction will always be in effect, and it has no expiration date.
Therefore, whether the property is leased or sold, no structures can be
built on the property, and it can be used only for parking.
Note that this ends the subject for the council, and that the council does
not intend to violate this covenant.
I would suggest that you make your decision based upon the law,
and we have copies of the deed for you.
I'm aware of this, which was brought to my attention last week.
I've reviewed this deed, and it does have that provision written as represented.
However, I would point out that if you were to turn to page three of the same
subparagraph B, which is the beginning of page most of the way through subparagraph B,
it goes on to state that it is further intended to read the agreement the
covenant provided in in subdivision A, which is obviously, if I'm
aware of it, there's no section apart from this.
It should be the cabinet providing in one, in subdivision A, a section two
shall remain in effect until July 1st, 2005, and restriction has been
avoided, or has terminated by the very order.
May we respond?
Sure.
Mr. Lori, our title attorney looked at that.
He said that there are portions of this deed that have expired, but that that
particular provision to which we have referred tonight is in effect and will
remain in effect for perpetuity.
So council members, I suggest that you be very careful about this.
If you are not sure, then tonight is the night for you to make the decision
that you're going to have to do your own due diligence and research this
very carefully, because we have consulted a title attorney who says that
portion of the deed to which we refer will exist in perpetuity.
So and he's done his homework.
So thank you.
With all due respect, Carol, Ben is our legal advisor.
We will take his tonight, and then he can talk to the title attorney that
the council will probably take Ben's advice tonight.
Anything else for us?
No, I just point out that I also am a title attorney.
So if that were the proper interpretation in this sentence,
it means nothing whatsoever.
It's in there.
So you feel confident we can proceed with a vote tonight?
I think that you are perfectly entitled to proceed to the vote as to
whether or not we're going to proceed looking at this.
If the vote is no, then that's the end of the discussion.
If the vote is yes, then we will just proceed through the process.
There will be other votes to be had as it moves along.
Anyone else?
Thank you, council.
I stand before you today as the CEO of the Boys and Girls Club of Ottawa County
to express our unwavering commitment to the betterment of our community,
particularly for our youth who are the future of this community.
Tonight we are here to discuss the important Teen Center Project,
specifically the construction of a much needed gymnasium
which has garnered significant attention and sparked a healthy dialogue within our community.
As you can see, we have additional community members here this evening
in support of our Teen Center Project.
They have come prepared to make a public statement in support of our project,
but given the statements we have already made directly to the council,
in addition to the negotiations we have attempted to make with Friends of the Coleman,
we don't find it necessary to spend any more time on this matter
and understand the council is ready to vote this evening and move forward.
I want to thank these community partners for taking the time
to show up this evening in support of the club
and for standing committed to the progress of our community.
First and foremost, I want to emphasize that we have approached this project
with an open heart and an earnest desire to collaborate with all stakeholders involved.
We understand the concerns raised by Friends of the Coleman
and want to assure the council and the community
that we have taken their questions and concerns seriously.
We have engaged in numerous conversations and meetings,
actively seeking to address the points of view and explore possible compromises.
Our commitment to collaboration extends far beyond mere words.
It is reflected in our actions.
We have made a conscious effort to engage in a constructive and inclusive dialogue,
working tirelessly to ensure that our project aligns
with the best interests of our community as a whole.
We value the input and expertise of Friends of the Coleman
and consider them an important partner in our collective mission
to improve the lives of youth in our community.
We have listened to their concerns regarding the impact of our project
on the historical significance of the Coleman Theater,
and we have taken steps to ensure that our plans are respectful at this cherished landmark.
We have also explored potential solutions to mitigate traffic
and parking challenges to alleviate any disruptions to our neighboring properties.
We have expressed our commitment to working with them to ensure events
at the Coleman Theater continue without any potential issues.
As an organization dedicated to serving the youth of Ottawa County,
we are deeply committed to enhancing the lives of young people.
The Teen Center project, including the gymnasium, is a crucial component of this commitment.
It will provide a safe and inclusive space for our teens to engage in physical activity,
educational programs, and positive social interactions.
We want to ensure the Council and the community that our dedication to serving
the youth of Miami is not limited to the immediate project, but extends for years to come.
The Teen Center will be a place where countless young lives will be positively impacted,
where lifelong friendships will be forged, and where dreams and aspirations will take root.
In conclusion, we want to thank the Council for their careful consideration of our project
and express our sincere gratitude to the Friends of the Coleman for their engagement
and their concern for our community's heritage.
We're committed to continuing this dialogue, to finding calming ground,
and to ensuring that the Teen Center project enriches the lives of our youth
while preserving the historical and cultural fabric of Miami.
We kindly ask for your support as we move forward, united in our shared goal of creating
a brighter future for the youth of our beloved city.
Together, we can make Miami an even better place to grow up and thrive.
Thank you for your time, and I'm happy to answer any questions.
I do have a letter from Councilman Eastiff, who's not here, and his wife went on a trip
that's pre-planned, so he did write a letter that I will read on his behalf in just a minute,
but I'm going to go first.
I told you guys earlier that I had met with Chief Cook on Friday, and I told you you're
going to hear a little more about that conversation, and this is the time for that.
When I met with her, when Beau and I walked in, first she told us how much she loved us,
but then she went on to say, you guys know we started something together,
and we started a mission that has a lot of momentum,
and she said, I'm not going to be able to be here and help you guys finish that.
I need you guys to finish this. We both assured her we would.
She loves her grandkids. She loves my grandkids. She loves her grandkids.
She loves everybody in this room's kids, because that's who Chief Cook was.
She loved every one of you, and she loved this community.
She knows what path we're on with this community right now.
This community is heading in the direction that hasn't been in a long, long time,
and I committed to her that day to lead without regret, and tonight I'm going to do that,
and since these guys are done, I'm making a motion to approve moving forward with at
least with the Boys and Girls Club. So now I'll read the Councilman's D-Step letter.
Ladies and gentlemen, community members, and distinguished guests,
today, although I could not be here in person, I'm writing to you advocate
for a cause that is close to our hearts, the construction of a much needed gymnasium
for our community in collaboration with the Boys and Girls Club, and the incredible work
being done by Mackenzie Garsland, nurturing the potential of our community's children.
Our community is a place where dreams are born, nurtured, and brought to life. It's a place where
our children's aspirations know no bounds and their potential is limitless. However, to ensure
that our youth can reach their full potential, we must provide them with the right tools and
opportunities. One of these crucial tools is access to safe, nurturing, and engaging
environment where they can grow not only academically, but also physically.
The Boys and Girls Club has a long history of serving as a pillar of support for our
community's youth. They've been a haven for countless children offering guidance, mentorship,
and educational programs that empower young minds, but today we're here to take the
next step in this journey. A gymnasium right here in our community would be more than just
a place to place for us. It would be a place where our children can learn the sexual life
skills. It's a place where they can discover the importance of teamwork, dedication,
and discipline. It's a place where they can build their self-esteem, learn set goals,
and work tirelessly to achieve them. This gymnasium will be a symbol of our commitment
to providing every opportunity for our children to succeed. Now, let me take a moment to
recognize Mackenzie Garson, a passionate advocate for our community's children.
Mackenzie has dedicated her time and energy to supporting our youth, ensuring they have access
to educational resources, mentorship, and caring community. Her tireless efforts have not gone
unnoticed, and we are proud to stand by her in this endeavor. Together with Mackenzie
Garson and the Boys and Girls Club, we can build a gym that will not only provide a space
for physical activity, but also serve as a hub of positivity, growth, and empowerment for our
children. It's an investment in our community's future leaders, athletes, and role models.
So I urge you all to support this vital project. Let's come together as a community,
as neighbors, and as friends, and make this dream a reality. By doing so, we not only build
a gymnasium, but we also build a brighter future for our children. A future where they
can thrive, excel, and become the best versions of themselves. Together, we can make a lasting
impact on the lives of our youth, and together, we can create a stronger, more vibrant community
for all. Thank you, Brian Easton. So for me, I think everybody agrees that we all support
the Boys and Girls Club. I don't think either side disagrees. It's a good thing.
For me though, my hang up is with the parking lot, and I know whenever
Goodfellas wanted the parking spaces there, and I didn't want to be a trend
where all of a sudden businesses are wanting parking spaces for wherever. So
for that vote, I was an A vote. And just to be consistent with that aspect of it.
A lot of you know what I do for a living. I've been in law enforcement in this area for
the last 30 years. I've seen a lot of our youth fall because they have nothing to do.
They have no place to go in this community. And therefore, a lot of them that we had to take
the juvenile jail, JVP, Kelly, Clarion Ward, or Vanita, or wherever. That's just wrong. We
need to stick together as a community and do something for our youth. And if we can't do
something for our youth, then there's something wrong with us. Because there's a lot of youth
out there that need our help now, and they're not getting it. We have nothing in this town
for youth to do. Nothing. And therefore, they just go out and they run amuck. So we absolutely
need to stick together and do something for them. I had a hard time with this vote.
I wasn't a vote, but as of now, I'm against it.
As a community, we need to do everything we can. I looked at both sides of it,
and to me, it's just the best decision. They're our future, and we've got to invest
in our future. I mean, I've had young kids still. I want them to have every opportunity
to make things successful at Colman. I'm on board. I would like to follow up, too, by saying
I know nobody up here, and I can speak for property stuff, too. Nobody here is against
the Colman. We're friends with the Colman. We're not against anybody. We love you guys.
You guys invest in an asset that's a city asset, and we thank you for that. You guys have
been great stewards of the Colman. I don't think for us it has anything to do with that.
For us, it comes down to just the kids. I think so it comes down to us that we
feel like we owe it to them to move forward with this, and is it ideal to make my motion?
Mayor, may I intervene real quick? Just to clarify, tonight is not a vote on an agreement.
Tonight is a vote of whether or not we should proceed to create an agreement.
So just to be clear, there's a lot of work to be done. There's a lot of issues that need
to be vetted and addressed, as Brad pointed out. To create an agreement, we have to look into
the issues that were brought forth today about the parking. We need to look at the number of
parking spots. We need to look at the environmental. We need to look at the water
runoff. All kinds of things still yet have to be vetted, and those things will be in future
decisions that we'll have to make once we come up with an agreement that everybody can agree
on that hopefully would meet the needs of everyone and address all the concerns. That
would be the goal, but again tonight is just a step to move forward to go vetted so that we
can do more engineering. The Boys and Girls Club had brought this to us because they were
at an impasse of not wanting to spend additional dollars on the engineering
if the council was not even interested in exploring it. So that's what they're seeking
today is just is the council interested? Would you be interested in exploring this agreement?
If so, there's more work to be done. Just wanted to clarify that. Williams?
Second word.
Contract C 23-34 with First National Bank and the amortization schedule for 36 months to 61
months to give related signing and payment authority to the city manager as designated.
A few meetings back we approved for a moon mover. I had it set up on three-year terms
and the budget actually had it set up at $39,952.80 which you all approved.
What I didn't realize everything up to this point we were doing on three-year terms on all
of them and I said okay this is three-year terms, but actually it was set up originally
on 60-month terms and for us to get to the $39,952.80 we would need to go
to 61 month terms. We'd get it to $39,592.00 which would keep us in budget
and that's why I need your approval to go along with this. First National Bank
is going to keep the same contract just change the amortization schedule.
Question approved. Second. Williams. Aye. Sunberg. Aye. Doppel. Aye. Parker. Aye.
Well, the pledge amendment 24-1, adjust the estimated carryover,
reduction of carryover, commerce funds, it's the same one with the MSUA.
Yes, this is for five funds that the council. Sunberg. Aye. Williams. Aye. Doppel. Aye. Parker. Aye.
13 other new business of any of which the residents close to this agenda.
14 staff reports. 15 mayor council community announcements. As mentioned earlier,
Chief Cook passed away yesterday. Her funeral arrangements are
she and Lane State at the Ottawa Community Building starting on Wednesday,
through Friday at four. The funeral will be Saturday at 16.
Before you get further, I thought you might want to address the flag conversation.
Oh yes. Sorry. And we're going to declare that all city flags be at half-mast
through Saturday at the funeral. All city flags be at half-mast. 16 city managers.
17. Doppel. Doppel. Aye. Sunberg. Aye. Williams. Aye. Parker. Aye.